Susan Rubin collection on International Women's Year and subsequent conferences SSC.MS.00792
Sophia Smith Collection
Susan Rubin collection on International Women's Year and subsequent conferences
1972-1990
Sophia Smith Collection
Rubin, Susan
SSC.MS.00792
3.5 linear feet (3 record cartons. Other materials: posters in flat file. )
Among her other roles in women's equity movements, Susan Rubin was a staff member on the National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year Secretariat, which was responsible for organizing the 1977 historic women's conference in Houston, Texas. This collection reflects Rubin's role as a staff member for the Commission working on the 1977 conference as well as later conferences, including Beijing, 1990.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, conference materials, workshop manuals, books, printed materials, and posters regarding International Women's Year, the National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year Conference in Houston 1977, and the 1990 follow up conference in Beijing. Of particular interest is the activity on the state level which is reflected in these records as well as on the national and international scenes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
2010 and 2011 accessions of materials likely came either directly from Susan Rubin or indirectly through Fran Worden Henry; Susan Rubin donated the third accession of materials directly in 2017.
Related Materials
See also: Patricia Rusch Hyatt papers, the Fran Worden Henry papers, and the Women's Rights collection.
Biographical / Historical
Among her other roles in women's equity movements, Susan Rubin was a staff member on the National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year Secretariat, which was responsible for organizing the 1977 historic women's conference in Houston, Texas.
Greatly influenced by the social and political times of the late 60s and early 70s, the growth of the women's movement, as well as the experience of her mother, Selma Fisher Rubin who taught at the University of Miami and filed one of the early EEOC sex discrimination cases, Susan Rubin's career has centered on working on women-related equity issues. Her jobs have included working with the American Association of University Women, the National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year (IWY), and the U.S Peace Corps. In her 2015 memoir, My Life on the Road, former IWY Commissioner Gloria Steinem noted that the 1977 National Women's Conference in Houston "may take the prize as the most important event nobody knows about" (53). At the time, Steinem and countless other feminists saw the November 18-21, 1977 gathering in Houston as a potentially life-changing event which would reaffirm and even expand women's rights. As state conventions to nominate delegates to the national convention were held across the country the summer of 1977, frequent clashes between feminists and a growing cadre of conservative women grew increasingly frequent, to the point even of physical violence. Such was the lead up to Houston 1977.
As a staff member for the National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year Secretariat, Susan Rubin was part of the Program and Policy staff that was responsible for organizing the 1977 historic women's conference in Houston, Texas. Among her assignments was the drafting of the workshop guidelines for Sexual Assault, Education and the ERA. Rubin was responsible for coordinating and managing the exhibit hall at the Houston conference which included over 200 exhibits and was the only part of the conference that was open to the public. She also coordinated the celebration program which oversaw the transfer of the conference's historic artifacts to the Smithsonian Institution.
Susan Rubin was born in Newark, New Jersey in 1952. Her family moved to Miami, Florida where she grew up, except for one year when they lived to Havana, Cuba and she attended first grade. Because of the Cuban revolution her family was required to leave Havana when all Americans were evacuated from the island. The family returned to Miami where Rubin lived until she moved to Austin, Texas in 1970 to attend the University of Texas. She received her BA in American history in 1973, and her MA in American History in 1976. Her course work and thesis for her MA focused on women's history, during a period when women's studies programs were just being developed and accepted as an academic discipline. Returning from Peace Corps she decided she needed additional management skills to contribute to her work with non-profits, particularly women-related causes. In 1984 she completed her MBA at Georgetown University.
As a Peace Corps Volunteer in Thailand, she worked with the Women Lawyer's Association of Thailand and the Asian and Pacific Centre for Women and Development at the United Nations. While living in Beijing, China she was an advisor on women's issues working with the All-China Women's Federation and the American co-sponsor on the first major bilateral conference following the Tiananmen incident of June 1989. Susan Rubin has two sons, Zack and Jesse, and resides in Washington, DC. As of 2018, she is Assistant Director of the National Association of Social Workers' Foundation where she provides strategic development and support for the Foundation initiatives including the international program.
International Women's Year, 1975; National Women's Conference (1st: 1977: Houston, Tex.); United Nations Commission on the Status of Women--History--Source; Houston 1977; Rubin, Susan; United States. Delegation to the Session of the United Nations Commission on the Status of Women; Rubin, Susan
- Susan Rubin International Women's Year materials, 1973-1979; Accession 2010-S-0087; 1.25 linear feet (1 record carton and 1 oversize flat file folder)
  Scope and Contents
  Selma Rubin correspondence, conference materials, workshop manuals, publications, and posters, all related to International Women's Year.
  - Correspondence to Dr. Selma Rubin (Susan Rubin's mother), 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Conference materials, workshop manuals, and publications, 1973-1979 (Box 1)
  - Posters, 1977-1978 (Oversize folder 1)
- Susan Rubin materials on International Women's Year and subsequent conferences, 1977-1990; Accession 2011-S-0028; 1.25 linear feet (1 record carton)
  - Houston Conference: records, pamphlets, memorabilia, 1975-1988 (Box 1)
  - Peace Corp Conference on Women and Development, Bangkok, Thailand: pamphlets and informational materials, 1979 (Box 1)
  - The First Sino-American Women's Conference: invitation packet, program, and memorabilia, 1990 (Box 1)
- Susan Rubin's materials related to IWY and Houston 1977, 1975-1990; Accession 2017-S-0044; 1 linear feet (1 record carton and oversize flat file folder)
  Pamphlets, newsletters, subject files, brochures, non-profit exhibit applications, state meeting notes, committee meeting notes, photographs from the International Women's Year (IWY) National Women's Commission, and Houston 1977 meeting as well as similar materials related to the The First Sino-American Women's Conference, aka the Beijing Conference.
  - IWY/National Women's Commission, and Houston 1977 conference, 1975-1979 (Box 1)
    Pamphlets, newsletters, subject files, brochures, non-profit exhibit applications, state meeting notes, committee meeting notes, and photographs
  - Beijing – "Holding Up Half the Sky" conference materials, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Posters: National Blueprint for Equality: National Plan of Action Adopted at the National Women's Conference, Houston Quote from Jill Ruckelshaus speech at The National Women's Political Caucus, California convention (signed by Gloria Steinem); "We're all Pro-Plan", 1977 (Oversize folder 1)